[snorts]
>> War ravaging the East since 1937 and
Japan's [music] invasion of China
reached Europe on the 1st of September
1939 with Germany's invasion of Poland.
It became global on the 7th of December
1941 when Japanese aircraft attacked the
American naval base at Pearl Harbor.
It touched every continent
and lasted for 6 years.
It ended with a new weapon for a new
age.
This is the history [music] of the
greatest of all man-made events.
These men are part of that history.
They are eyewitnesses to the triumphs
and tragedies of the war wherever it was
fought.
Their testimony is part of the story of
how our world was made
by those who could pay
and those who could no longer meet
the price [music] of empire.
In the last episode of The Price of
Empire with British and American forces
crossing the Rhine with the Red Army
surging over Germany's eastern border,
the The of Adolf Hitler and the Third
Reich [music] is inevitable.
In the final episode,
peace in Asia [music] will follow peace
in Europe after the detonation of a
terrible new weapon.
On the 28th of March, 1945, the Supreme
Allied Commander, General Dwight D.
Eisenhower, [music]
acting on his own initiative, advised
the Soviet leadership that his troops
would be advancing on the line
Erfurt-Leipzig-Dresden.
[music]
He made it clear that Berlin was not his
objective.
Stalin, delighted, replied that he too
regarded Berlin as of no consequence.
Churchill was appalled. He argued that
the post-war settlement demanded that
the Allies meet the Russians as far east
as possible.
Churchill's influence, Britain's
influence, was on the wane.
On the 28th, three army groups began
their move towards the line
Erfurt-Leipzig-Dresden.
The British second moved from its
bridgehead at Wesel. The US first and
third trapped the German 89th Corps
around Giessen.
Four days later, the US ninth linked
with the first at Lippstadt.
In a little over three weeks, they would
make contact
with the Red Army.
On April the 15th, after the Ruhr Pocket
had been cut in two, Field Marshal
Walter Model was invited to surrender.
Model replied that he was bound by his
oath to Adolf Hitler, and a formal
surrender was out of the question.
Instead, he dissolved his army group.
325,000
German troops were taken prisoner.
On the 20th of April, the Propaganda
Ministry in Berlin publicly denounced
Army Group B as traitors.
Model, who knew that the Soviets had
indicted him for war crimes, shot
himself in the head.
Also in April,
Nuremberg, so symbolic of Nazism, fell
to General Patch's 7th US Army, and
American forces crossed the Danube.
On the 25th, American and Soviet troops
made contact.
On the same day, the Red Army completed
its encirclement of Berlin.
Hitler declared that Berlin was to be a
fortress.
Defensive preparations were made in
depth, but resources were far from
elite.
The 12th Army, west of the city,
comprised 12 divisions that were a grab
bag of raw recruits, misfits, leftovers,
and veterans. Von Manteuffel's 3rd
Panzer Army, north of the city,
comprised nine divisions, none of which
was Panzer.
The total deployed in defense of the
capital was some 50 indifferent
divisions. Coming towards them were
almost 200 divisions of the Red Army.
And as they came on,
they scorched the earth.
Everywhere that men make war, there is a
tragic toll of brutalized, raped, and
murdered women.
Not even the most inspired apologist can
suggest that these victims were paying
for crimes they had committed.
Germany maintained 500 military
brothels.
As the Red Army surged into Berlin, it
is estimated that 80,000 survived rape,
and 10,000 rape victims died, many by
suicide.
The figures are, predictably, disputed.
>> I went on the hill to have a bit
observation if I can see any Russian
trucks and nothing.
And on the bottom,
there was a lady. She was hiking high
for goats she had.
And then I went down.
Yeah, yeah, you come here. You've been
already home? I said, "No."
Oh, then you don't know. I said, "What
do you mean, don't know?"
Your sister has been raped by a truck of
Russian soldiers.
And the last Russian soldier mutilated
her and dropped her in the next grenade
hole.
>> The Soviet offensive was designed to
ensure the fall of Berlin no later than
May Day.
May the 1st.
Soviet forces began to move on April the
12th.
On the 15th, Hitler issued a special
order of the day.
"For the last time," it said, "our
deadly enemies, the Jewish [music]
Bolsheviks, have launched their massive
forces to the attack." Hitler's order
said that if every soldier did his duty,
the last assault of Asia will crumple
and Europe will never be Russian.
8,983
Soviet guns opened up.
And more than 6 million men and women of
the Red Army began to move.
Zhukov's first Belorussian Front in the
center, Konev's first Ukrainian Front in
the south, Rokossovsky's second
Belorussian in the north,
raced each other for the prize.
Zhukov's offensive began when 140
searchlights operated by female soldiers
[music]
were turned on in the eyes of the enemy.
But the front line was found to be
mostly deserted.
In the city, up to 10,000 [music]
Germans were hanged for defeatism, many
from lampposts.
April the 20th was Hitler's 56th
birthday.
He decorated some members [music] of the
Hitler Youth for bravery,
then went into the Führerbunker [music]
16 and 1/2 m below the Chancellery
Garden for the last time.
>> Now at last, after all the ghastly years
of toil, blood, tears, and sweat, the
climax of total German defeat is reached
with the death of Berlin.
>> On the 28th, Hitler learned that
Heinrich Himmler had been behind the
opening of armistice negotiations in
Italy.
Reichsmarschall Göring, who had slipped
away south, signaled Hitler that since
the Führer was trapped in Berlin,
perhaps he should take control of the
German state.
Hitler ordered both Göring and Himmler
stripped of their rank and arrested.
He also ordered SS-Obergruppenführer
Hermann Fegelein shot, which he was, for
attempting to slip out of Berlin in
civilian clothes.
He then married Fegelein's
sister-in-law, Eva Braun, and drew up
his last will and political testament,
in which he explained that
"I desire to share the fate that
millions of others have taken upon
themselves, in that I shall remain in
this city."
"Furthermore, I do not want to fall into
the hands of enemies [music] who, for
the delectation of the hate-riddled
masses, require a new spectacle promoted
by the Jews."
On April 30th, after first successfully
testing the poison on [music] his
beloved dog Blondie, Hitler and his new
bride bit down on cyanide capsules,
[music] at which point Hitler, to be
certain, shot himself in the temple.
The Red Army was 200 m away.
"The German wireless broadcasts serious
important news," [music]
said the announcer, and with Bruckner's
Seventh playing as it had with the
announcement of the fall of Stalingrad,
the solemn voice continued,
>> [music]
[music]
>> It is reported from the Führer's
headquarters that our Führer, Adolf
Hitler, fighting to the last breath
against Bolshevism, fell for Germany
this afternoon in his operational
headquarters.
Mrs. Goebbels murdered her [music] six
children, then she and her husband
committed suicide. The next day the
Reichstag fell and the red [music] flag
was famously hoisted on its roof.
>> [music]
>> General Helmuth Weidling, commanding the
military garrison, [music] surrendered
the city.
The battle for the capital had cost more
than 300,000 Soviet casualties.
Perhaps a similar number of German
casualties and in addition 480,000
German prisoners who had failed in their
attempt to break out west [music] to
surrender to the American, British and
French forces from whom they expected
kinder treatment.
>> [clears throat]
[music]
>> Members of the Grand Alliance were by
now making contact all along the front.
Montgomery's forces [music] met
Rokossovsky's on the line
Wismar-Wittenberg and on May the 4th,
Montgomery received [music] the
unconditional surrender of all German
forces in Northwest Germany, Denmark and
the Netherlands.
I took by the arm.
Bottom
>> On May the 7th, the Germans signed the
unconditional surrender.
Before May the 7th, all of Germany's
Axis partners but one had [music]
already changed sides. Hungary, Romania,
Italy were fighting with the allies by
the time Berlin fell.
Only Japan remained to oppose the United
Nations.
Churchill and Roosevelt's [music]
successor, Harry Truman, were ready to
declare May the 7th victory in Europe,
VE Day, but their Soviet allies were
not. They insisted on a separate
surrender ceremony in Moscow. So VE Day
became May the 8th.
The war in the west was over.
The prisoners of war were liberated.
>> We're in this camp
and suddenly a tank appeared.
Next thing I know is the
tank
turned round and went went down the far
corner of the camp barrier.
Smash the whole thing to the ground.
Coming here
>> [cheering]
>> I went
and a fellow Brit, well, I think he was
a Brit,
was shot up.
Waved to us.
That was the end of the war for us.
>> The war in the west was over. Jewish
people who had been hidden for years by
brave countrymen could show their faces.
>> The day came when I was leaving
and Jan Rosier went to his little money
box
and took out 100 guilders for me.
And he gave me 100 [music] guilders.
And he said to me, "For the train or the
bus or whatever you need.
And don't forget [music] to write."
And uh
so
>> [music]
>> write I did all my life.
>> [cheering]
>> The war in the west was over. 160,000
collaborators were arrested. A thousand
were executed. Most of those who had
served went home.
>> Marvelous. A feeling of joy, really.
It had been a very long slog, so it
wasn't a sort of tremendous celebration.
Uh, we just sort of rather said, "Ah,
thank god that's over, you know?" That
That was rather the feeling.
>> The war in the East continued.
A firebomb raid on Tokyo in March had
killed 87,793
people
and had destroyed 38 [music] square
kilometers of the city.
>> [music]
>> On April the 1st, American forces had
landed on the largest of the Ryukyu
Islands, an archipelago that stretches
from Taiwan to the most southerly of the
main home islands, Kyushu. They had
landed on Okinawa.
>> We got our assignment first. I was going
on watch at a 4:00 watch in the morning
to 8:00.
And when you stand on watch,
they come and call you cuz you can't get
up. We don't have alarm clocks, you
know?
But you better make that [music] watch
or you're in big trouble.
>> For the invasion of Okinawa, 430 assault
transports were loaded at 11 ports from
Seattle to Leyte.
On April 1st, 1,300 ships were massed
offshore and the 50,000 men of General
Simon Bolivar Buckner's 10th Army went
ashore against very little opposition.
General Ushijima, commanding the
Japanese 32nd Army, having concentrated
his force south of the Shuri line.
>> Just minutes after 4:00.
It hit the superstructure.
Everything went blank.
We were aft. All the machinery aft.
Machinery forward was still good.
>> Over the next few days, the Japanese
launched kamikaze assaults on the
invasion fleet, which did not wholly
relent in all the weeks of fighting that
lay ahead.
By the end of the Okinawa campaign, the
suicides of 1,465
kamikaze pilots had accounted for 29
ships sunk,
120 damaged, and 3,048
sailors killed.
>> It was a kamikaze took us out.
We found his body with a parachute.
Couldn't understand why he had a
parachute on.
Because he might have been shot down in
Ie Shima.
That's the answer to that.
I will tell you this, and this is hard
for me to tell you.
He did his job, [music] and he did it
well.
I fired on planes.
I don't know if I have hit a plane
because
the sky lit up with the shells.
They do go down, but who did it, you
don't know.
In time, as I got older,
I realized
he didn't mean it.
He did a job.
>> On the 9th of April, American invasion
forces opened their main offensive
against the well-planned fortifications
of the Shuri line.
And it was terrible fighting and slow
progress.
Okinawa north of the line was cleared
with little real opposition. The Motobu
Peninsula had been cleared by April
20th.
But it was deep into May before Japanese
resistance was broken in the south.
The capital Naha fell on the 27th and
Shuri Castle, [music] key to the
defensive line, on the 29th.
On June the 18th, [music] with the
battle almost won, General Buckner was
killed by the effects of a shell
exploding overhead.
He was the highest-ranking American to
be killed in action.
To the surprise of the Americans who had
not known it elsewhere in the Pacific,
the Japanese began to surrender as their
morale collapsed.
On June 22nd, General Ushijima committed
suicide.
Casualty lists were catastrophic.
Japanese casualties exceeded 110,000.
Americans, 40,000 in battle and nearly
10,000 more
to kamikaze.
>> This is just part of the price being
paid for victory in the Pacific.
>> [music]
>> It hurt you worse than it hurt them.
Remember is not pleasant.
I don't blame anybody.
But people don't know your problem.
I have to excuse myself because I'm
usually a jolly fellow, a fairly wise
guy.
>> The Okinawa casualties formed the basis
for American projections of casualty
rates for the invasion of Japan.
The estimate was that taking Kyushu, the
first of the home islands, would cause
268,000
American casualties.
Double the total battlefield deaths
suffered by America in the war to date.
That figure weighed heavily in the
debate that would resolve the next phase
of the war, the use of a new weapon.
The leaders of the Grand Alliance met
[music] at Potsdam.
But not the familiar faces.
Harry S. Truman was now president of the
United States, and by the time the
conference adjourned in July, Winston
Churchill would be missing from the
lineup.
The 1945 election, Winston Churchill and
his party would be dumped in a
landslide.
>> Mr. Attlee summed up for Movietone the
situation as it appeared to a man about
to be Prime Minister.
>> The Labour Party's great victory
shows that the country
is ready
for a new policy
to face new world conditions.
>> The The that was reached at Potsdam was
the last between the members of the
grand coalition.
Shared out influence in Europe.
The consequences were famously described
less than a year later by Winston
Churchill.
"An iron curtain has descended across
the continent." He said.
"Behind that line lie all the capitals
of the ancient states of [music] Central
and Eastern Europe. Warsaw, Berlin,
Prague, Vienna, Budapest, [music]
Belgrade, Bucharest, and Sofia."
And he might have added the cities of
Ukraine, Belarus, and the Baltic states
for these had not always been part of
the Russian Empire.
At [music] Potsdam, the leaders faced
the opportunity to create a peace based
on compassion and cooperation. [music]
Instead, they replaced World War with
Cold War.
Their priority was the Soviet Union's
agreement to enter the war against
Japan.
Price they were prepared to pay was the
temporary occupation of the countries of
Eastern Europe, which continued until
1990.
Potsdam issued a demand for Japan to
surrender which said, "The alternative
for Japan is prompt and [music] utter
destruction."
Words composed in the knowledge that on
the 16th of July, the first atomic bomb
had been successfully detonated at
Alamogordo in New Mexico.
Among scientists working on the project
were eight refugees from Nazi
persecution.
When leading scientist Robert J.
Oppenheimer saw the blast, he recalled a
verse from a Hindu sacred book.
If the light of a thousand suns were to
rise in the sky at once,
the decision whether to use the new
super bomb rested with the commander in
chief, Harry S. Truman.
Truman ordered that the first special
bomb
be dropped as soon as conditions allowed
in early August. So, on August the 6th,
the B-29 Enola Gay dropped Little Boy
from 9,600 m.
It detonated 575 [music]
m above the city, generating a blast of
300,000°
C for 1/10,000 of a second.
It was not designed [music] to blow a
city up,
but to knock it down.
>> I don't know.
>> [music]
[music]
>> 100,000 were killed, up to 100,000 more
doomed. It was, said Harry Truman, the
greatest thing in history.
Though no one really knew whether it
would shorten the war.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Despite Hiroshima, there was no response
from Japan to the Potsdam [music]
declaration. So, Truman ordered the
second attack.
>> That's the atomic bomb exploding at
Nagasaki.
The film was taken in a B-29 many miles
away.
>> Fat Boy was [music] detonated over
Nagasaki.
35,000 were killed according to the
Americans. 74,800
according to authorities in Nagasaki.
On the day that Nagasaki was bombed,
the Transbaikal and Second Far East
Fronts of the Red Army invaded
Manchuria.
>> [music]
>> The First Far East Front moved from
Vladivostok.
>> During the campaign in Manchuria, the
Soviet Union took 674,000
Japanese prisoners. Half survived their
captivity.
Of the Japanese who had settled in
Manchuria, they had been promised fresh
virgin plains ready to welcome armies of
fresh migrants.
67,000 starved to death and 11,000 died
at the hands of vengeful Chinese.
When the Supreme Council for the Conduct
of the War met in Tokyo on the 9th of
August, there was bitter conflict
between those arguing for peace and the
war party.
It was the Soviet invasion, rather than
Hiroshima, which forced the issue.
On the 10th, the day after the Soviet
invasion, the Japanese [music]
sent a Morse code signal to the effect
that they accepted the Potsdam demands
subject only to there being nothing
which would compromise the role and
sovereignty of the emperor.
On the 11th, Japan received the Allied
reply. On the 14th of August, the
emperor ordered acceptance of the terms
and recorded the [music] message that
was broadcast to his people the next
day.
They had never heard his voice.
Now they heard Hirohito speak.
>> [music]
>> "The war situation has developed not
necessarily to Japan's advantage." He
told them.
"Therefore, our empire accepts the
provisions of the joint declaration."
Hirohito did not say what the joint
declaration was. So when he had finished
speaking, a popular announcer came on
air to explain that it meant that the
war was over.
People went home and waited. When polled
after the war, only 4% of Japanese
believed that they would be humanely
treated. The [music] others believed
what they had been told, that all they
could expect was starvation, torture,
and death.
Shortly after dawn on August the 28th,
45 US C-47 transports touched down at
Atsugi Air Base.
US Colonel Charles Tench stepped onto
the tarmac. He was the first conqueror
ever to set foot on Japanese soil.
>> I just want to say America no hate
Japan.
I just came to die.
>> [music]
>> On the deck of the USS Missouri, 6 years
and 1 day after Hitler had launched his
invasion of Poland, General MacArthur
called forward General Wainwright who
had surrendered his command in the
Philippines and General Percival who had
surrendered his command in Singapore.
They stood at his shoulder as he
accepted [music] Imperial Japan's
unconditional surrender.
The war in the East was over.
After 8 years [music] of fighting, the
Japanese released all of their Chinese
prisoners of war.
All 56 of them.
And the Allied [music] prisoners of war
who had survived were liberated.
>> Four corvettes [music] in the Australian
Navy entered Ambon Harbor.
I can still see them coming down that
bay
to recover us.
By this time, there was only a 101 of us
left.
I forget just where where I would have
been, but I it was on the ship anyway
coming home.
I heard we heard Bing Crosby singing,
"Don't fence me in."
I kid you not.
>> [cheering]
>> Oh, give
me land,
lots of land
under starry skies above.
Don't
fence me in.
>> Those who had fought could go home.
>> Let me ride
the wide open [singing and music]
country that I love.
Don't
fence me in.
>> Return of peace after the world's most
devastating war.
VJ Day, victory in the second half of
the global conflict.
>> I got off the trolley car with my big
duffel bag on my back and my army
uniform. I've been away for 2 years and
here is my sister with her newborn baby
[music] and my little mutt along side of
her. Pulls away from me, comes running
up the block and my sister is screaming,
"I'm sorry, sir. I'm sorry. She's never
done that. My dog is a good dog." And
the dog is running, running and he's all
over me and I'm crying in tears [music]
and she didn't know me till she got
within like 5 ft. My little dog knew me.
Came home and lived happily ever after.
>> The greatest man-made event in history
[music] was a war of such colossal
proportion that the cost in money is
hard to comprehend.
>> The tally in human life even more
difficult.
For every two people that the United
States lost in the war, Britain, her
Commonwealth and Empire lost three.
The Japanese, 12. The Germans, 22.
The Soviet [music] Union,
184.
The aggregate figure of 27 million dead
for the Soviet Union [music] is probably
the best guess.
And for China,
more than 20 million.
No one can accurately calculate the
final death toll,
but it is surely dwarfed by the total of
lives not lost, but permanently affected
by a war which can never be understood
in statistics.
>> I don't speak for the army,
or what I was involved in.
I just gave you the general outlook of
how we progressed.
But the individual fighting,
with bayonets,
hand grenades, that that is the war.
That is war.
>> [music]
>> For so long a display of colors defining
this or that nation's sovereignty over
others, the map of the world has now
become a great patchwork.
The vast land empires are no more.
The great maritime empires, Spain,
Portugal, France, the Netherlands, the
British, all gone.
But why?
Empires are acquired, conquered for
trade, resources, territory, and because
of a conceit common to all empire
builders.
That because their cultural and
political DNA is superior,
they are right to inseminate other
societies.
This has been the story of such a
conceit.
Two imperial dreams drove their people
into the Second World War.
The Japanese and German empires expanded
violently.
They collapsed, bankrupt.
And their collapse sounded the death
knell of the old imperial system.
The price of empire can be expressed in
monetary terms,
but the price also involves [music]
values which have nothing to do with
money.
The enormous convulsion of the Second
World War,
infected as it was in every part by the
bacillus of racism,
allowed people to see that independence
and identity
are incorruptible values.
To plunder, to slaughter, to steal,
these things they misname empire.
Wrote the Roman historian Tacitus 2,000
years ago.
Those who could have been embraced as
liberators were loathed as conquerors.
They misnamed their conquests empire
and they paid the price.
>> [music]